Guide to the Clarence Wharton Papers, 1804-1956 MS 019
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Clarence R. Wharton papers
1804-1956
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Wharton, Clarence Ray, 1873-1941
MS 019
10 Linear Feet
The Clarence R. Wharton Papers includes Wharton's papers, correspondence, research files and manuscripts related to Texas history. The correspondence pertains primarily to the preparation and/or publication of his works, such as "Gail Borden, pioneer," "Wharton's History of Fort Bend County," "Remember Goliad," "L'Archeveque," and others. Also included is manuscript material of other authors.
(20 boxes)
Historical Note
Clarence Ray Wharton, son of Frank B. and Ella Ray Wharton, was born in Tarrant County, Texas, on Oct. 5, 1873. He attended county schools, taught from 1888 to 1892, studied law and was admitted to the bar around 1893. He began a law practice in 1885 in Decatur with Charles V. Terrell, moved in 1897 to Richmond and then to Houston to join the law firm of Baker, Botts, Baker, and Lovett in 1901. On Aug. 5, 1902 he married Adele Spoonts, and together they had four children. He was made full partner of the law firm in 1906, and as a corporate attorney represented Houston Lighting and Power, Houston Gas and Fuel, and Houston Electric companies. Wharton was the first chairman of Houston Community Chest, and prominent in the American Red Cross during World War I. He was active in the Harris County Historical Society, reaching vice president in 1923. He was very well known for his many articles and published works on Texas history. He died in Houston on May 1, 1941 and was buried in Glenwood Cemetery.
Excerpted from The New Handbook of Texas, 1996.
Scope and Contents
The Clarence R. Wharton Papers includes Wharton's papers, correspondence and manuscripts related to Texas history. The correspondence pertains primarily to the preparation and/or publication of his works, such as "Gail Borden, pioneer," "Wharton's History of Fort Bend County," "Remember Goliad," "L'Archeveque," and others. Also included is manuscript material of other authors.
Restrictions on Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
The materials were received in 1970-71 from Carroll and Harris Masterson III as part of the Masterson Texana Collection.
Related Materials
The Masterson Texana Collection (book collection) is a good source for published materials related to the manuscript materials. See http://www.rice.edu/fondren/woodson/search_masterson_books.html.
See also Harris Masterson I Papers MS468. Online guide available at http://www.rice.edu/fondren/woodson/mss/ms468.html.
Arrangement
Materials are organized into eight series:
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence, 1849-1956 (boxes 1-4)
Series II: Legal, 1927-1940 (boxes 4-5)
Series III: Speeches, 1918-1940 (boxes 4-5)
Series IV: Thomas F. Harwood materials, 1923-1925 (box 6)
Series V: Visuals (box 6)
Series VI: News clippings/scrapbooks, 1930s (boxes 6-7)
Series VII: Texas History Research Files (box 8)
Series VIII: Printer matter/manuscript materials, 1804-1939 (boxes 8-20)
Accruals
No future additions are expected for this material.
Index Terms
Subjects
Republic of Texas; Revolution (Texas: 1835-1836); Literature
Document Types
financial records; documents; corrrespondence
Places
Texas -- Goliad; Texas -- San Jacinto; Texas -- Fort Bend County; Texas -- Brazoria County
Subjects (Persons)
Borden, Gail, 1801-1874; Briscoe, Andrew; Dixon, Sam Houston; Fannin, James Walker, 1806?-1836; Harwood, Thomas F.; Hogg, James Stephen, 1851-1906; Rister, Carl Coke, 1889-1955; Santa Anna, Antonio López de, 1794?-1876; Swisher, John Milton, 1819-1891; Bastrop, Baron de, 1759-1827; Bailey, George M.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1849-1956 (boxes 1-4), 253638
  - W.P. Huff to Jas. Knight, 1849, 253672 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1920s, 253671 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Concerning "Pictorial History of Texas," 1926-1927, 253670 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - American Historical Society, April 19, 1928-Dec. 30, 1939, 253669 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mary R. Bolton, 1928-30, 253668 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Concerning San Jacinto book, 1929-31, 1938-39, 253667 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B.O. Baker, 1930s, 253666 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General, Sept. 1930-Jan. 1936, 253665 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Concerning Texas history book, 1930-31, 1938-39, 253664 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Houston Independent School District, 1931-32, 253663 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Re: Gail Borden, May 1935-Jan. 1939, 253662 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Re: Mirabeau B. Lamar, Oct. 1935-Dec. 1935, 253661 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General, Feb. 1936-1942, 253660 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Re: Jean L'Archeveque, Nov. 1936-Aug. 1939, 253659 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Re: Wm. Scurlock, Feb. 1937-March 1937, 253658 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Re: Charles S. Taylor, June 1937-Nov. 1937, 253657 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Re: Ft. Bend County, Aug. 1937-Feb. 1939, 253656 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Re: Ft. Bend County, March 1939-Jan. 1940, 253655 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Re: Texas history, 1937-38, 253654 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Re: Judge Baird, Sept. 1938-Jan. 1941, 253653 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Re: Texas history, 1939-41, 253652 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Lena Archebech, Aug. 1939, 253651 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Re: History of Ft. Bend County, 1939-40, 253650 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Re: Beauregard Bryan, March 1939-Feb. 1943, 253649 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jesse H. Jones, 1952, 253648 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Isaac B. DeSha, 1953, 1956, 253647 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publishers, 253639
    - Bobs-Merrill Co. Publishers, 1934, 253646 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Kingsport Press, 1923, 1929-30, 1933, 253645 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Southern Publishing Co., 1930-42, 253644 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Southwest Press, 1931, 1934-35, 253643 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Turner Co., 1935-39, 1941, 253642 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Publishers, general, 1930-31, 1933-35, 1939, 253641 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d., 253640 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series II: Legal, 1927-1940 (boxes 4-5), 253623
  - Southwest Press contract, 1935, 253637 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Publishing agreement with Naylor Co., 1939, 253636 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Royalty contract with Southern Publishing Co., 1933, 253635 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Contract between C. Wharton & Banks Upshaw & Co., 1935, 253634 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Moses Jones v. J.R. Williams, 253633 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Heirs of John Bricker v. Keystone Mills Co., c. 1933, 253632 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Gulf Oil Corp. v. Marathon Oil Co., c. 1936, 253631 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Gulf Oil Corp. v. Marathon Oil Co., c. 1937, 253630 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Gulf Oil Corp. v. Marathon Oil Co. (appendix), c. 1937, 253629 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - El Paso Electric Co. v. National Labor Relations Board, c. 1939, 253628 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Jurisdiction of the Alcade Courts in Texas prior to the revolution [c. 1927], 253627 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - List of papers and documents in custody of Dr. Hill, 1940, 253626 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Pamphlets (legal and speeches), 1935, 253625 (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
  - Pamphlets (legal and speeches), 253624 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Series III: Speeches, 1918-1940 (boxes 4-5), 253613
  - Speeches, 1935, 253622 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Address, Harris Co. Taxpayers League, 1931, 253621 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "A Day of Destiny," Texas Bankers Association, 1918, 253620 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Industrial Peace in Texas," Texas State Manufacturers Association, 1939, 253619 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "It May Take a Thousand Years," Baylor University Commencement, 1938, 253618 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Labor Laws of Texas," Executive Committee of Texas Manufacturers Association, 1940, 253617 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - C.V. Terrell portrait presentation, State Teachers College, Denton, 1936, 253616 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Utility Situations in Texas," Galveston City Attorneys Association, 1929, 253615 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, general, 1920s-30s, 253614 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Thomas F. Harwood materials, 1923-1925 (box 6), 253607
  - Gammel's Book Store, 1923-25, 253612 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scribners & Sons, 1924-25, 253611 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Eugene Digges, 1924, 253610 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - E.L. Shettles, 1924, 253609 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 253608 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series V: Visual materials (box 6), 253594
  - Goliad, Tex., 253606 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Andrew Briscoe house, 253605 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Perry house, Peach Point, 253604 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Elizabeth Powels' Place, 253603 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Phelps house, "Orizimbo", 253602 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Mrs. Edwin Shepherd, others, 253601 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - William Summers tombstone, 253600 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - C.R. Wharton, 253599 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. John A. Wharton & daughter, 253598 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Palmetto, 253597 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Old train station in Houston, 253596 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Assorted images, 253595 (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
- Series VI: News clippings/scrapbooks, 1930s (boxes 6-7), 253585
  - Various, 253593 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "Let Us Have Industrial Peace", 253592 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - "100 Years Ago Today" column, c. 1936, 253591 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Photocopies of "100 Years Ago Today", 253590 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - "Signers of Declaration of Independence of Texas", 253589 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "George M. Bailey", 253588 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, pictures, verse, 253587 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Information (and misinformation) gathered while writing a history of Ft. Bend County, 1935-39", 253586 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series VII: Texas History Research Files (box 8), 253570
  - Gutzom Borglum, 253584 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Josephine Wharton Bradley, 253583 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. J.E. Irvin, 253582 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Invitations, 253581 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Secretary of Commerce statement, 1943, 253580 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Statement by Vice President Wallace, 1943, 253579 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Sam Houston biographical information, 253578 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - List of Clarence Wharton's works, 253577 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "Remember Goliad" brochure, 253576 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Prospectus: "History of Fort Bend County, 1822-1900", 253575 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Prospectus mailing list, 253574 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Ingroa letters (photocopies), 253573 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Wharton family genealogy, 253572 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 253571 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Series VIII: Printer matter/manuscript materials, 1804-1939 (boxes 8-20), 253479
  - Subseries A: Reviews, 253565
    - Coronado's Children, 253569 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - From Quebec to New Orleans, 253568 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Judge Winston's Life of Jefferson Davis, 253567 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - The Texas Navy, 253566 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Subseries B: Transcriptions, 253542
    - Letter re: Harrisburg and the railroad, 1839, 253564 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - "Counties in Texas in which San Jacinto Veterans are known to be buried", 253563 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - List of Colonel Fannin's men, 1836, 253562 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Jas. W. Fannin letters, 1830-32, 253561 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - "Six Letters from Texas," 1836, 253560 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - "List of people who received Mexican land in Harris County", 253559 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - "More Desperadoes Arrested," 1876, 253558 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - "Letter from Hall's Command, " 1878, 253557 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - "Letter from State Trooper," 1877, 253556 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - "Arrest of the Stage Robber," 1877, 253555 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - "From One of McNelly's Boys," 1876, 253554 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - "State Trooper," 1878, 253553 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - "Letter from Lt. Hall's Command," 1877, 253552 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - "McNelly's Men and the Desperadoes," 1876, 253551 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - "On Sail Boat," 1878, 253550 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - "From a Soldier's Reminiscences," 1850, 253549 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - "Texas Telegraph and Register," Oct. 1835-April 1836, 253548 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Letters and articles concerning Gail Borden; bound, 253547 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Texas items from LA newspapers, 1804-37; bound, 253546 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Lapham letters; bound, 253545 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Lost Towns; 1830s newspaper notices; bound, 253544 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "Wild Oats Sowing"; ts. carbon transcription of print; bound, 1937, 253543 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C: Manuscripts, 253486
    - "Sidelights of the Battle of San Jacinto," Vol. 1&2, (2 c.) R. B. Blake Ts., ts. carbon; bound, 253541 (Box 10, Folder -)
    - Chapters for San Jacinto book, ts. carbons, 253540 (Box 10, Folder -)
    - "History of Fort Bend County" Ts., ms. alterations; bound, 253539 (Box 10, Folder -)
    - "Fort Bend County," Ts., ms., photographs, clippings, notes; bound, 1938-39, 253538 (Box 10, Folder -)
    - Preface to "Fort Bend County," ts. carbon, 253537 (Box 10, Folder -)
    - Index to "History of Fort Bend County," ts., 253536 (Box 10, Folder -)
    - Bibliography for "Fort Bend County," ts. carbon, 253535 (Box 10, Folder -)
    - Translation of H. Ehrenberg's "Fahrten und Schicksale Eines Deutschen in Texas," E.W. Bartholomae M.A. thesis, ts., ms. annotations; bound, 1925, 253534 (Box 11, Folder -)
    - "Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Letters" Ts., photocopy, clippings; bound, 253533 (Box 11, Folder -)
    - "Life of Governor Hogg," George Bailey Ts. carbons (2 volumes), inserted clippings; bound, 1927, 253532 (Box 11, Folder -)
    - "The Need for a New Approach to the History of Texas," R.G. Santos, 253531 (Box 11, Folder -)
    - "One Hundred Years Ago Today, " Vol. 1 & 2 Ts.; bound, 1935-36, 253530 (Box 12, Folder -)
    - "Colonel John M. Swisher Remembrances of Texas and Texas People," 1879; ts.; bound, 253529 (Box 12, Folder -)
    - "Pictorial History of Texas Photos" with ms. notes; bound Illustrations with notes. 2 copies; bound Illustrations with notes, variations; bound 1937 Illustrations with notes, variations; bound, c. 1939, 253528 (Box 13, Folder -)
    - "Men Who Fought with Houston at San Jacinto" (2 volumes), Sam Houston Dixon Ts. carbons with alterations, 2 volumes; bound, 253527 (Box 13, Folder -)
    - "Berber Davenport File of Fannin Documents," Ts., ms., photocopies, clippings; bound, 1933 Ts. carbon; bound, 253526 (Box 14, Folder -)
    - "Some Critical Reflections on the Christian Religion," W.H. Wilson Ts., with letter; bound, 1929, 253525 (Box 14, Folder -)
    - "The Nueces-Rio Grande Border," Paul S. Taylor Ts., annotations, additions; bound, 253524 (Box 14, Folder -)
    - "Jack Tolman," Ts., ms., printed articles, memoirs, photo, holograph letters; bound, 253523 (Box 14, Folder -)
    - History of Texas "Notes prepared by R.D. Holt…;" bound Ms. ts., maps, illustrations; bound Ts. carbon; bound, 253522 (Box 15, Folder -)
    - "L'Archeveque and other Sketches," Ts., ms., photographs; bound, 253521 (Box 15, Folder -)
    - "Thirty Presidents," Ts, illustrations, alterations; bound, 1931, 253520 (Box 16, Folder -)
    - "The Whartons of Old Brazoria," Ts., ms., photographs, letters, clippings; bound, 253519 (Box 16, Folder -)
    - "The Whartons of Old Brazoria," Bob Boyce Ts., ms.; bound, 1923, 253518 (Box 16, Folder -)
    - "Baron de Bastrop," with R.W. Moore's M.A. thesis Ts., ms., photocopy, maps, photographs; bound, c. 1932, 253517 (Box 16, Folder -)
    - "The Vindication of Don Carlos Barrett, Horne," Ts, ms. alterations; bound, 1930, 253516 (Box 16, Folder -)
    - "A Report of Hurricanes, and Conditions Indicating a Hurricane in the Vicinity of Galveston, Texas, from 1867 to 1916," Rex D. Frazier Ts.; bound, 1921, 253515 (Box 16, Folder -)
    - "Remember Goliad," ts.; bound, 253514 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - "The Goliad Campaign," Ts., added printed pages, clipping; bound, 1933, 253513 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - "El Presidente: Life of General Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna" Ts.; bound Ts. carbon; bound, 253512 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - "Santanta, the Great Chief of the Kiowas, and His People" (3 vol.) Ts. carbons (2) with added illustrations; bound Printed, ms. and ts. notes, illustrations; bound, 253511 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - "Charitable Trusts," Ts. carbon; bound, 253510 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - "Alphabetical List of Soldiers in the Goliad Campaigns," Aterbury, 253509 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - "Sterling, the Thirteenth Governor of Texas," ts., 253508 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - "The Phantom State of West Texas," ts. carbon, 253507 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - "Lysander Wells' Letter," ts. carbon, 253506 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - "Heroes of the Revolution," ts. carbon, 253505 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - "The Governors of Texas," ts. carbon, 253504 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - "A Day in Old Brazoria," ts. carbon, 253503 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - "What is the Farmer's Future?," ts., 253502 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Introduction to "Garden Club of America," ts. carbon, 253501 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - "Charges of Judge Evermont Ward," ts., 253500 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - "A Short History of Texas," ts. carbon, Josephine Wharton Bradley, 253499 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - "A Short History of Texas," Josephine Wharton Bradley Ts, ms., ts. alterations; bound, 253498 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - "Gail Borden" (first draft), ts. annotations, 253497 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Chapter 11: "Gail Borden Goes to London," ts. carbon, annotations, 253496 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Bibliography for Gail Borden, ts. carbon, 253495 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Gail Borden, Jr., Pioneer Ts. carbon with ms. alterations; bound, 1939, 253494 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - "America, Knight Errant of the Ages," ts. carbon, 253493 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - "A Renegade Son," ts. carbon, 253492 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - "Boundary Settlement," ts. carbon, 253491 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - "East of the Rio Grande" (play), ts. carbon, 253490 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - "Houston—A Seat of Government of Texas," ts. carbon, 253489 (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - Unnamed manuscript, ts. carbon, 253488 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Manuscript annotations for The Life of Philip, Late Duke of Wharton, 253487 (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Subseries D: Proofs, 253480
    - "Pictorial History of Texas," Illustrations, ms. alterations; bound, 1930; Illustrations, ms. alterations; bound, 1930 (pages cut to trade size); Illustrations, ms. alterations; bound, 1935; Without illustrations, with ms. corrections and additions for Vol. 2; bound First edition proofs with few corrections (2 volumes); bound, 253485 (Box 19, Folder -)
    - "History of Fort Bend County," Ms. alterations/additions, inserted clippings/illustrations; bound, 1939 Title, table of contents, illustrations, 1939 Newsprint off-print, Chapter XII Ts. And ms. additions and alterations, inserted clippings, Annotated; bound, 253484 (Box 20, Folder -)
    - "The Heroes of San Jacinto," Dixon & Kemp Ms. and ts. additions and insertions; bound, 253483 (Box 20, Folder -)
    - "San Jacinto: The Sixteenth Decisive Battle," Ms. alterations; bound First proof, 253482 (Box 20, Folder -)
    - "Remember Goliad," Inserted clippings, illustrations, ms. alterations, photocopies, c. 1931; bound, 253481 (Box 20, Folder -)